בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is עין ה Ayin Hey
75, we start at the משנה. Mishna.
I just want to make just a two-second comment about yesterday because
it ended with this complicated case about one house opening into another,
opening into another, opening into the courtyard. So the end of the
גמרא Gemara sort of said that the problem was there about making
it יחיד במקום עובדי כוכבים. yachid bemakom ovdei kochavim. So the way
I expressed that was to creating all the three houses as one
house was turning it into a scenario of יחיד במקום עובדי כוכבים.
yachid bemakom ovdei kochavim. רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosafot following רשי Rashi
says otherwise, says that the problem was, was that we didn't want
the two houses basically just to remind you of the scenario, the
scenario was essentially here you have a חצר chatzer and here you
have a house of a non-Jew and here you have houses of
Jews or I guess בית bayit or whatever בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
anyway opening into one another, so that technically there was only one
Jew in the courtyard with the non-Jew and the questions were would
these guys make עירוב eruv amongst themselves so that they could also
carry in the courtyard. So the way I explained it was the
problem was that it was turning it into a case of יחיד
yachid but רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say no, it starts as
a case of יחיד במקום נכרי yachid bemakom nochri and we don't
want you guys to encourage it. We don't want you, you know,
we don't want this guy to be living here all, you know,
all alone with the non-Jew. So which effectively he is because those
are the ones that have, you know, immediate access into the courtyard.
So that's the way they explain, we don't want these guys to
join in because we don't want to encourage this person to be
alone with the non-Jew. The other point was, was that the relevance
of making it one house, if you remember the larger theme there
was the question about what defines a courtyard that a לחי lechi
or a קורה kora is enough and the position of רב Rav
that you needed a courtyard to have two houses. So according to
רשי Rashi according to primarily תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says the issue
here is, is that when you take although these are multiple houses,
only one of them opens up into the courtyard. So he understands,
I mean it's a huge תוספות Tosafot as you can see and
he has a couple of explanations, but he basically understands that the
issue at stake is when does those houses becoming an עירוב eruv
because they're so closely connected? They're not just opening into the same
courtyard but they're opening into one another, you know, there's attached houses,
when would it make and be considered to be one house? And
as we know, to allow a courtyard with a לחי lechi or
קורה, kora, you need two houses. Alright, so that's just a little
clarification. I know it's a complicated case and you could again see
by the size of the previous תוספות Tosafot that, you know, and
that's not a תוספות Tosafot type of a תוספות. Tosafot. Some תוספות
Tosafot are big because they're asking problems from other סוגיות sugyot and
they're trying to reconcile. Here it's just because he's trying to make
sense out of the case. So it really is just three different
explanations about this case we did yesterday, but the basic theme being
as I said that the way רשי Rashi and תוספות Tosafot understand
the concern is those two shouldn't do it because they don't want
to encourage that guy and the idea of to what degree because
their houses that are connected are they considered separate houses or a
single house for the idea that a courtyard needs two houses to
use a לחי lechi or a קורה. kora. Yes.
Is there any concept of being concerned about a Jew living with
a נכרי nochri because of השקפה hashkafa issues, only the safety issues?
According to the way the גמרא Gemara expressed so far it's because
of safety issues and then where the גמרא Gemara constantly speaks about
if there are other people that are common in the courtyard then
we're not concerned and so on. Okay, now we move on to
a, I would like to say a new topic, it's not totally
new, it's something we've seen before, and we've actually been referenced many
times, so hopefully this now looking at it in its original location
in this משנה Mishna should be pretty straightforward. שתי חצרות, Shtei chatzerot,
so the משנה Mishna עין ה עמוד א. Ayin Hey Amud Aleph.
שתי חצרות זו לפנים מזו, Shtei chatzerot zo lifnim mizo, two courtyards,
one behind the other. עירבה פנימית, Eirva pnimat,
so again I'll just draw this we've seen this multiple times,
but here we've got
two
courtyards, I guess call them A and B, and the only way
B gets out to the street is through A, okay?
So, and you've got everyone has their own houses etc. So the
thing is that if B hasn't made an עירוב, eruv, then you
have people that themselves haven't made an עירוב eruv that are going
to necessarily be moving through A, okay? And therefore that could that
will disrupt any עירוב eruv that A will make amongst its own,
its own members. Alright, because here you have a group of people
that basically is a zone, a no-carry zone as it were, and
they're going to be moving through, so it's like they're all mixed
together. The question is going to be what if B makes an
עירוב eruv and A makes an עירוב? eruv? So these guys are
good in B, these guys are good in A, but the B
people are constantly moving through A and B and A haven't made
an עירוב eruv together. So does that disrupt A? A doesn't disrupt
B because A always goes in one direction. A can always be
ignored. But B will always be moving through it. So if they're
distinct, even if they've made an עירוב, eruv, to what degree do
they disrupt the A? Now it's not because they're walking through, I
want to clarify again. You can walk wherever you want as long
as it's not more than two thousand אמות amos outside. Okay, but
the point is, since they are walking, since the presence there, and
they'll be carrying their objects, so, you know, here they carry their
objects from their house into their courtyard, there's also the likelihood of
their carrying their courtyard objects from B to A because of the
constant traffic. And therefore, because of that sense of presence, is that
enough to disrupt? And that's the issue we're going to look at.
So let's take a look. שתי חצרות זו לפנים מזו. Shteichatzarot zu
lifnim mi'zu. You have two courtyards, one behind the other. עירבה פנימית
ולא עירבה חיצונית. Eirva pnimis velo eirva chitzona.
If the inner one, B, made an עירוב eruv and not the
outer one, הפנימית מותרת, hapnimis muteset, B is okay because they can
ignore A. A, the traffic always goes, you know, out towards the
street. So הפנימית מותרת והחיצונית אסורה. hapnimis muteset vehachitzona asura. B is
okay and A is forbidden. החיצונית ולא הפנימית. hachitzona velo hapnimis.
Now let's say A made an עירוב eruv not B. שתיהן אסורות.
shteihem asurot. So B is obviously אסור, asur, they didn't make an
עירוב, eruv, and A is אסור asur because you've got a, you
know, an אסור asur place that's constantly, and the people of that
place constantly, sort of as it were, present in your zone. So
you know, B makes its presence felt in A, and therefore if
B is אסור asur in its own zone, it disrupts A as
well. עירבה זו לעצמה וזו לעצמה. Eirva zu le'atzma vezu le'atzma. If
A and B each made their own respective עירוב. eruv. זו מותרת
בפני עצמה וזו מותרת בפני עצמה. zu muteset bifnei atzma vezu muteset
bifnei atzma. That's the logical idea. So B is allowed and A
is allowed, each one is permissible. רבי עקיבא אוסר החיצונית. Rabbi Akiva
oser hachitzona. And Rabbi Akiva says no, even in this case, A
is a problem. שדריסת הרגל אוסרתה. she'drisat haregel osartah.
The trampling through of B, again emphasizing, you know, their physical presence,
makes it forbidden. And the way the גמרא Gemara basically, even though
you've got an עירוב eruv here and an עירוב eruv here, they're
not עירב eirev together, and since B is seen as always present
in A, so they are, as it were, A doesn't have an
עירוב eruv for all of its people, because A's people includes B.
B is always present in A, conceptually. And therefore, A's עירוב eruv
is not good unless it also includes B. And the way the
גמרא Gemara explains רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is רגל המותרת במקומה,
regel
hamuteset bimkomah, right, because B is permissible in its own place,
אוסרת שלא במקומה. oseret shelo bimkomah. Okay? Even though B is permissible
in its own place, it makes a problem in its, not, in
its not local place, in its, you know, in a different place,
because since it's going moves through A, conceptually it's present in A,
that creates problems for the people of A. That's what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says. But the חכמים Chachamim disagree. They say אם מותרת
במקומה אינה אוסרת שלא
במקומה.
Im muteset bimkomah einah oseret
shelo bimkomah. What question? I'm the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma.
What תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma?
Because the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said זו, oh,
you mean the חכמים Chachamim are the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? We
haven't read that yet. וחכמים אומרים, VeChachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim
say, אין דריסת הרגל אוסרתה. Ein drisat haregel osartah. No, B does
not make A forbidden. So that sounds like a reiteration of what
we just said, so the גמרא Gemara will deal with that. שכח,
shachach, now the next application is very straightforward, it's really the same
thing as the first, except rather than the scenario of not having
made an עירוב eruv one of the courtyards, it's you made an
עירוב eruv but one guy forgot to participate. Which at the end
result becomes the same case, becomes the case of not having an
effective עירוב. eruv. שכח אחד מן החיצונית ולא עירב. Shachach echad min
hachitzona velo eirev. If one of the outer ones forgot, of A
forgot, and one of the guys of the household and did not
participate in the עירוב, eruv, so effectively A doesn't have an עירוב.
eruv. הפנימית מותרת והחיצונית אסורה. hapnimis muteset vehachitzona asura. B is okay,
A is no good. מן הפנימית ולא עירב. min hapnimis velo eirev.
If one of the guys of B forgot, so effectively there's no
עירוב eruv for B.
שתיהן אסורות. shteihem asurot. B is אסור asur for obvious reasons, and
A is also אסור asur because B is like it's always present
in A. Now,
נתנו עירובן במקום אחד. Natnu eiruvam bemakom echad. Let's say they put
their עירוב eruv in one place, meaning they made an עירוב eruv
together, okay, and so they unified their places. Now the גמרא Gemara
will explain that the actual עירוב eruv is sitting in courtyard A,
okay, in one of the houses in courtyard A, but they made
a unified עירוב. eruv. ושכח אחד, Veshachach echad, and one of the
people forgot, or forgot to participate. A and B made a unified
עירוב eruv and one of the members forgot to participate. בין מן
הפנימית בין מן החיצונית ולא עירב, Bein min hapnimis bein min hachitzona
velo eirev, whether it was a guy from A or B and
didn't make the עירוב, eruv, שתיהן אסורות, shteihem asurot, they're both forbidden.
Okay, this even basically even the חכמים Chachamim agree that if they
made one joint עירוב, eruv, which normally makes it better, right, because
they're all together, what could be bad? But one of the guys
forgot, so even though normally let's say if A forgets, we can
just ignore A, right? Because, right,
if we made separate and A forgot, B would be okay because
A doesn't influence B. But here they're all one. So they're all
one, everybody now impacts everybody. to one house. So now it's one
big עירוב eruv and now let's say A forgot, one of the
members of this uni-, B did not make one on its own.
You have one unified עירוב. eruv. So in the case where you
have a unified עירוב, eruv, it normally solves problems, but if one
guy forgot now you got problems.
We can do the whole ביטול bitul thing, right?
What? Yeah, yeah, I mean there might be some solutions of ביטול
bitul or whatnot, but that's the point. So normally if A if
A was a problem, B would still be okay. But if they're
a unified עירוב eruv then even if A is a even if
one guy in A forgot, they all now are no good. Okay,
ואם היו שני של יחידים אינם צריכים לערב. ve'im hayu shenei shel
yechidim einam tzerichim le'arev.
Let's say in courtyard A and courtyard B, there's not multiple houses.
There's only one guy who lives in courtyard A and one guy
who lives in courtyard B. So if that's true, you don't need
an עירוב. eruv. Right? Because A doesn't need you know because why
would that be? Because there's only one guy
anyway.
Right? If you've got only one guy here in B and one
guy in A, B doesn't need an עירוב. eruv. He's just all
alone for B. A doesn't need an עירוב. eruv. Right? Now it's
true that B can't carry into A, right? Because they are different
courtyards and they have not made an עירוב eruv together. Yes? Everybody
with me here? Okay, but so we're not talking about carrying in.
What we're talking can A carry in its own zone? So it's
saying yeah, no problem carrying in your own zone, because B really
is totally fine. They don't need an עירוב. eruv. Now that is
only according to the חכמים Chachamim. who disagree with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. According to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, even though it's only one
guy here and one guy here, since if B were in the
in together with A you would need an עירוב, eruv, then even
when they're separate B creates a problem. Okay, so the last scenario
is pretty similar to if B made an עירוב eruv by itself
and A made an עירוב eruv for itself. Except instead of talking
about that each one made their own עירוב, eruv, it talks each
one has an individual house there's only one house so there's no
need for an עירוב. eruv. And again it's the question of if
B is okay in its own zone, can it still create problems
for A? And that's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
the חכמים. Chachamim Everybody sufficiently confused? Okay, yes.
All right, what?
There's one point. What are we concerned about? Just their presence?
Because they're considered to be present, they're considered according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, let's say even if they did make an עירוב, eruv,
but if B is considered present in A, they're considered as if
they were members of the courtyard of B of A, right? Because
B is always moving through A, they're always considered according to רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva as members of the courtyard. So even if they've
made their own עירוב, eruv, they haven't made an עירוב eruv together
with A. So therefore the you can't carry in the A zone.
You could only carry in the A zone if all the members
of A have made an עירוב. eruv.
Right, but if A's made an עירוב eruv and B's present, right,
B אוסר oser A. Right.
Why? Because since they're always going through it, it's like they are
members of that courtyard.
So were the people who live in A going to see the
people who haven't made I
mean it's more I see your point. It's not a practical issue.
If you wanted to express it practically you would say, well maybe
we're concerned that people will carry from B to A. But that's
not actually the issue because if B hasn't made an עירוב eruv
nobody is carrying in B anyway. So what so there's no likelihood
that B is going to carry to A because B they can't
even carry in their own zone. It's more of a conceptual point.
The הלכה halacha is you can't carry in a courtyard unless all
of the members of the courtyard have participated in an עירוב. eruv.
So because B is going through A, they would consider them as
members of the courtyard. Which is why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
I don't even care if B is totally made their own עירוב.
eruv. They haven't made it together with A and they're part of
the courtyard of A. And the חכמים Chachamim say no there's a
limit. If they themselves their zone is okay, then even when we
sort of see them in A, we see them as like a
non-problematic presence.
So we're talking about A and B but really conceptually they're considering
them as one.
That's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is definitely considering them as one. If
you want to carry in A, if you want to carry in
B you can ignore A. Okay. Yeah.
Let's say there was another מבוי mavoi on the side of B.
Can we not go with that? If there's another מבוי mavoi on
the side of B then none of this applies because it's only
because B has no choice but to go through it. All right,
let's see now what the גמרא Gemara says. As if that weren't
confusing enough, although we've seen it a number of times, so hopefully
you're getting it. Let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
says. כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי ינאי, Ki ata Rav Dimi
amar Rabbi Yannai, so when Rav Dimi came in the name of
Rabbi Yannai he said, זו דברי רבי עקיבא. Zu divrei Rabbi Akiva.
This is the position of Rabbi Akiva. Now now you would say
like Michael the last thing the thing that said דברי רבי עקיבא,
divrei Rabbi Akiva, but no, he's saying the whole משנה mishnah is
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Really there are not two opinions in the
משנה, mishnah, which is wild and we'll see how the גמרא Gemara
deals with it. But he wants to stake out a third position
of the חכמים Chachamim that is even more lenient.
זו דברי רבי עקיבא דאמר אפילו רגל המותרת במקומה אוסרת שלא במקומה.
Zu divrei Rabbi Akiva de'amar afilu regel hamuteret bimkomah oseret shelo bimkomah.
Even B that's okay in B zone when they made an עירוב
eruv they make a problem in A. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval Chachamim
omrim, the חכמים Chachamim say, כשם שרגל מותרת אינה אוסרת, keshem sheregel
muteret einah oseret, the same way when if B has made an
עירוב eruv they cannot make a problem for A, כך רגל ה
kach regel ha אסורה אינה אוסרת, asura eina oseres, even if B
hasn't made an עירוב, eruv, they cannot make a problem for A.
So רב ינאי Rav Yannai wants to say that there is a
position that is even more radical that says that B never influences
A. Okay, that even if they haven't had an עירוב, eruv, they're
totally separate. Who the heck cares what's going on in B? A
is its own courtyard, B never influences A. Okay, so now we
have three positions. Okay, we have רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that says
B always influences A, always impacts A. Okay, we have what we
have thought was the sort of תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of our
משנה, mishna, which says B when it's אסור assur influences A. And
we have who is this, רב אימי? Rav Imi? רב ינאי.
Rav
Yannai.
רב ינאי, Rav Yannai, according to רב ינאי, Rav Yannai, he says
B never influences
A, even if it's אסור, assur, even אסור, assur, B never has
an impact on A. Okay? B always influences A, B never influences
A, and only when B is אסור assur does it influence A.
Okay? So we thought we only had these two positions. He's saying,
no, no, no, the חכמים Chachamim say even when B is אסור
assur it never impacts A and the whole משנה mishna really was
not all רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. So let's see what he's going
to do. What? Well, let's see what he's going to do with
the משנה. mishna. Okay, so let's take a look.
תנא, Tna, so we taught in our משנה, mishna, עיר החיצונה ולא
פנימית שתיהן אסורות. ir hachitzona velo pnimis shteihen assuros. If the outer
one made an עירוב eruv and not the inner one, okay, if
A made an עירוב eruv and not B, that's one of the
things the משנה mishna set up upfront, then A is a problem
as well. So that seems like why is A a problem? Because
B is a problem, which again seems like that middle position. When
B is אסור, assur, that's when it influences A. Okay, so שתיהן
אסורות. shteihen assuros. מאני? Mani? Who is this going like? אילימא רבי
עקיבא, Ileima Rebbe Akiva, if it's רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, מאי אריא
רגל האסורה? mai irya regel ha'asura? Why is it giving this scenario
when B is אסור? assur? אפילו רגל המותרת נמי, afilu regel hamutteres
nami, even when B is מותר mutter he thinks it creates a
problem. אלא לאו רבנן, Ella lav Rabbanan, it must be the Rabbis
and you see that the Rabbis say that it's only an issue
for A when B is אסור. assur. The גמרא Gemara says no,
לעולם רבי עקיבא. lo'olam Rebbe Akiva. No, when it says when B
is אסור assur it influences A, that's not the Rabbis, the Rabbis
would say B never influences A. So who's it going like? It's
going like רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. ולא זו אף זו קתני. velo
zo af zo katani. So what the משנה mishna is saying is,
it's saying if B is אסור assur it influences A, and then
saying, and you know what? Even if B made their own עירוב,
eruv, they don't influence A, B, I mean they do influence A,
B always influences A. Okay, so the משנה mishna starts by saying
if B is אסור assur it influences A, and then it says
and even if they made the עירוב eruv and they're מותר, mutter,
they still influence A and the whole משנה mishna is רבי עקיבא.
Rebbe Akiva. But the חכמים Chachamim would say that B never influences
A even when it's אסור. assur. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Where were we? ולא זו אף
זו קתני.
velo zo af
zo katani. Not only this when it's אסור assur does it influence
A, but even when it's מותר mutter it impacts A. תנא, Tna,
so let's look at another line in the משנה. mishna. עיר זו
לעצמה וזו לעצמה. ir zo la'atzmah ve'zo la'atzmah. When the משנה mishna
says A and B make their own respective עירוב, eruv, separate עירוב,
eruv, זו מותרת בפני עצמה וזו מותרת בפני עצמה. zu mutteris bifnei
atzmah ve'zu mutteris bifnei atzmah. A is permissible by itself and B
is. B does not influence A, presumably because B is מותר. mutter.
So the גמרא Gemara says טעמא, ta'ama, why does B not influence
A? דעירבה, de'eirva, because it made its own עירוב eruv and it's
מותר. mutter. הא לא עירבה, ha lo eirva, if it had not
made its עירוב, eruv, שתיהן אסורות, shteihen assuros, it would create a
problem, right? So the משנה mishna basically, the גמרא Gemara is saying
like this, the simple read of the משנה mishna says if B
is אסור assur it creates a problem for A, if B is
מותר mutter it doesn't create a problem for A. That's the middle
position. B is a problem only when it's אסור. assur. So how
do you explain that? So we now have a line that say
when B is מותר, mutter, A is okay, which means that when
B is אסור, assur, A is no good. So that's a middle
position, that's not your extremes. So who is that going like? So
the גמרא Gemara says והאי
תנא דאמר רגל המותרת אינה אוסרת רגל האסורה אוסרת. vehai tanna de'amar
regel hamutteres eina oseres regel ha'asura oseres. So you see
what this תנא tanna is saying is, it's a middle position. If
B is okay, it doesn't create a problem. If B is forbidden,
if it's אסור assur in its own location, it's אוסרת, oseres, it
creates a problem for A. So that's exactly the middle position which
you are denying. You are saying רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva is one
extreme, it always creates a problem, and the חכמים Chachamim. are the
other, it never. But here we say no, it's okay because B
is okay, which is the middle position. So מאני, mani, who is
this going like? אילימא רבי עקיבא היא, ileima Rebbe Akiva hi, if
it's רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, אפילו רגל המותרת נמי. afilu regel hamutteres
nami. He would say that even when B is מותר mutter it
creates a problem. אלא לאו רבנן היא? ella lav Rabbanan hi? It's
the Rabbis and you see they're a middle position. They say that
if B is okay, A is okay, I'm okay you're okay. If
B is no good, right, then A is no good, so you
see a middle position, but that they basically feel that it's only
okay because B is
okay. So point number one. מדסיפא רבי עקיבא, mideseifa Rabbi Akiva, משלבא
רבי עקיבא. mishelava Rabbi Akiva. Since in the end it says זו
דברי רבי עקיבא, zu divrei Rabbi Akiva, right, what's the case? We're
dealing with a case where the משנה Mishna explicitly says the debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים. Chachamim It's the case
about B is okay, you know, עירוב בפני עצמה, eruv bifnei atzma,
you know, oops, בפני עצמה, bifnei atzma, and A is okay, right?
Right? בפני עצמה. bifnei atzma. That's what it said. And it says
if you have if this is a and this is okay they're
both okay, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said no A is no
good, right? Because because B makes it no good. That was the
case where the משנה Mishna expressed their debate. So what the חכמים
Chachamim, are saying, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, look, we
see two things. First of all, we see that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva is disagreeing with the previous position, which means that until now
we have not been talking about רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. You can't
say the whole משנה Mishna is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Number two,
we see that the only reason A is okay is because B
is okay. If B was no good, A would be a problem.
That's this middle position, not your extreme where you're trying to say
that A is always okay regardless of the story of B. So
clearly the משנה Mishna is articulating a middle position of the חכמים,
Chachamim. not the extreme of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or the extreme
of your idea of the חכמים. Chachamim So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says no, כולה רבי עקיבא
היא. kula Rabbi Akiva hi. I'm going to now we get to
rewriting the משנה. Mishna. I'm going to rewrite the משנה Mishna that
it's all רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. כולה רבי עקיבא היא וחסורי מחסרא
והכי קתני. kula Rabbi Akiva hi vechasorei mechasra vehachi katani.
It's missing some words. Here's how it should be read. עירבו זו
לעצמה וזו לעצמה, eirvu zu le'atzma vezu le'atzma,
if B made a separate one and A made a separate one,
זו מותרת בפני עצמה וזו מותרת בפני עצמה. zu miteret bifnei atzma
vezu miteret bifnei atzma. Each one is allowed separately. Now that sounds
like that because because B is מותר, mutar, A is מותר. mutar.
It's a middle position, but either one of the alternatives would not
be that way. במה דברים אמורים, bamei devarim amurim, so now the
גמרא Gemara adds in some words. When is that true that B
being מותר mutar makes A מותר? mutar? שעשתה דקה. she'asta daka. It
made a little barrier. You might remember the דקה, daka, the little
barrier, and that allowed B to partition itself off of A. אבל
לא עשתה דקה, aval lo asta daka, if there's no barrier, חיצונית
אסורה דברי רבי עקיבא, chitzonit asura divrei Rabbi Akiva, then even if
B was made a separate עירוב, eiruv, A would still be a
problem. שרבי עקיבא אוסר את החיצונית מפני שדריסת הרגל אוסרתה, sheRabbi Akiva
oser et hachitzonit mipnei shedrisat haregel oserata,
because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says if B always creates a problem
on A. So basically, it completely changes the משנה. Mishna. The משנה
Mishna said if B makes its own עירוב, eiruv, A is safe,
and that clearly indicates a middle position that argues on רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. And the גמרא Gemara says no, the reason that we
have to add some words, the reason it said if B made
an עירוב eiruv A is safe is only when there's like a
barrier between B or A. But basically, B always creates a problem
for A, and that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position. וחכמים אומרים אין
דריסת הרגל אוסרתה, veChachamim omrim ein drisat haregel oserata, that it does
not make it אסור. asur. So basically, a real serious rewrite of
this משנה Mishna complicating things to get it to be that the
חכמים hachamim aren't saying a middle position, they're saying an extreme in
the opposite direction. So מתיבי רב ביבי בר אביי, mativei Rav Bibi
bar Abaye, the גמרא's Gemara not done. It says no, wait, let
me just get through this. It does not like this read of
the משנה. Mishna. ואם היו של יחידים, ve'im hayu shel yechidim, the
end of the משנה Mishna says if A has only one person
in it and B has only one person in it, אין צריכין
לעירוב, ein tzerichin le'eruv, you don't have to make an עירוב. eiruv.
Which suggests, השתא רבים, hashta rabim, if there are many people in
B, צריכין לעירוב, tzerichin le'eruv, it's a problem. Now, אלמא רגל המותרת
במקומה אינה אוסרת, alma regel hamuteret bimkoma eina oseret, that when B
is okay, there's only one guy, A does not have a problem.
רגל האסורה, regel ha'asura, when there are many people living in B,
אוסרת, oseret, it makes problems for A. So again it's a middle
position. It's not that B never creates a problem for A. If
there's a lot of people in B it is, and it's not
that B always creates a problem for A. If there's one guy
in B you're okay. So again you see the משנה's Mishna articulating
a middle position. When there's one guy in B, it's okay for
A. When there's multiple, it's no good. So it's this middle position
that when B is okay, A is okay. When B is no
good, A is no good. So the גמרא Gemara says ועוד, ve'od,
and in addition, מתיבי רבינא. mativei Ravina. Let's look at the other
case in the משנה. Mishna. שכח אחד מן החיצונית ולא עירב, shachach
echad min hachitzonit velo eirav, if one of the guys of A
forgot and didn't make an עירוב, eiruv, פנימית מותרת, pnimat miteret, B
is okay. Fine. וחיצונית אסורה. vechitzonit asura. שכח אחד מן הפנימית ולא
עירב, shachach echad min hapnimit velo eirav, if one of the guys
of B forgot, שתיהן אסורות, shtehen asurot, so they're forbidden. So this
is a perfect proof of a middle position, right? Because this basically
goes to the case of the משנה Mishna which says that if
B made their own עירוב eiruv and A made their own עירוב,
eiruv, it says then A is okay. But if one of the
guys of B forgot and the whole עירוב eiruv became no good,
then A became no good, which is exactly the middle position. When
B was okay, A was okay. As soon as a guy in
B forgot and B became no good, A became no good. So
that's exactly the middle position. That when B you know, when B
is bad, A is bad, when B is good, B is good.
Not like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it's always a problem, always bad.
And not like the position here of רב ינאי, Reb Yanai, that
it's always good, A is always good regardless of B. It's this
middle position that it depends. We'll just put depends. Okay, so
anyway, so that's the point. It's clear in the משנה Mishnah a
middle position. It says, if B made an עירוב eruv and A
made an עירוב, eruv, A is good. If one guy forgot, A
becomes no good. So clearly it's neither of the two extremes that
you are arguing for.
So let's take a look. השתא רבים, Hashta rabbim, if there's many
people in B, תנן, tnan, אמר רגל המותרת במקומה אינה אוסרת. Ammar
reigel hamoeteres bimekoma einah oseres. When,
I'm sorry, I misread that. I skipped that. רבינא Ravina we're up
to. שכח אחד מן החיצונה ולא עירב הפנימית מותרת והחיצונה אסורה. Shachach
echad min hachitzona velo eirev haptimiz muteres vehachitzona asura. שכח אחד מן
הפנימית ולא עירב, Shachach echad min haptimiz velo eirev, if one of
the B guys forgot, שתיהם אסורות. sheteihem asurot. טעמא, Tama, the reason
A becomes a problem is ששכח, sheshachach, one of the guys at
B forgot. So when B became no good, A became no good.
הא לא שכח, Halo shachach, but when B was still okay, שתיהם
מותרות, sheteihem muteres, A would be okay. אלמא רגל המותרת אינה אסורה,
Alma reigel hamoeteres einah asura, so you see it's not that it's
always good or that it's always no good. It depends. When B
is okay, A is okay. רגל האסורה, Reigel ha'asura, when B became
no good, אוסרת, oseret, then B became no good. So it's a
lot of effort to point out what seems to us obvious in
the משנה, Mishnah, that the position that argues on רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva is not an extreme that it's always good, but that it
depends. As long as B is good, A is good. When B
is no good, A is no good. אלא, Ela, the גמרא Gemara
rejects this whole approach of רב דימי. Rav Dimi. כי אתא רבין
אמר רבי ינאי, Ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yanai, when רבין Ravin
came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, now this also in the name
of רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yanai. The earlier position of רב דימי Rav
Dimi was רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yanai, this is רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yanai,
but his version is the following. ג' מחלוקת בדבר. Gimmel machloket badavar.
Again, what רבי ינאי Rabbi Yanai is trying to do is to
put out there a third position that is much more מיקל, meikel,
even than the position that is in our משנה, Mishnah, that says
no matter what's going on with B, it will never influence A.
So rather than trying to argue that no, that that's the whole
משנה Mishnah is רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, we're going to admit that
there's a middle position in the משנה, Mishnah, but we'll still going
to say that there's a third position that's even more מיקל meikel
than that.
This is based on the רמב"ם Rambam
because the השתא דאתית להכי? Hashta de-atit le-hachi? Yes, yes, so you
guessed it. So there's three opinions. תנא קמא סבר, Tana kama savar,
the first opinion is just like what you've been saying, which is
obvious in the משנה. Mishnah. It's a middle position. רגל המותרת אינה
אסורה ורגל האסורה אוסרת. Reigel hamoeteres einah asura vereigel ha'asura oseret. When
B is okay, A is okay. When B is no good, A
is no good. You're right, that's what's going on in the משנה.
Mishnah. רבי עקיבא סבר, Rebbi Akiva savar, אפילו רגל המותרת אוסרת. afilu
reigel hamoeteres oseret. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says it's always bad. Whatever's
going on with B, A is always a problem. ורבנן בתראי Verabbanan
basrai is the point that we were trying to argue before was
universal, now we're just saying it's a third position. רבנן בתראי סבר,
Rabbanan basrai savar, when it says חכמים אומרים, hachamim omrim, right, and
the חכמים hachamim seem to reiterate what רבנן Rabbanan were saying is
no, the חכמים hachamim are going even further. And they're saying, כשם
שרגל המותרת אינה אוסרת, keshem she-reigel hamoeteres einah oseret, the same way
when B is okay, A is okay, כך רגל האסורה אינה אוסרת,
kach reigel ha'asura einah oseret, even when B is a problem, A
remains okay. B never influences A. Okay, so that was a little
confusing. It was confusing because it was a really forced read in
the משנה, Mishnah, but the upshot is very simple. The upshot is
that our משנה Mishnah makes it clear that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
says that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva basically says I'll draw it again,
board is getting too cluttered. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva basically says
that A and B always have to make an עירוב. eruv. B,
right, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says B is always a problem. The
משנה Mishnah seemed to say the middle position,
תנא קמא, Tana Kama, right, sometimes, okay.
If B is okay, A is okay.
If B is no good,
A is no good, right?
That's clearly what the sense of the משנה Mishnah where it says,
so if B didn't do it, then A becomes a problem. If
B did it, then A is okay. If one guy in B
forgot, A is a problem. If everybody in B remembered, A is
okay. That was a simple sense of the משנה. Mishnah. B is
good, A is good, if B is bad, A is bad. Comes
along this רבי ינאי, Rabbi Yanai, this statement of רבי ינאי Rabbi
Yanai and says there's a third position out there, that the חכמים
hachamim who say B does not create a problem for A is
not a reiteration of תנא קמא. Tana Kama. The חכמים Chachamim are
saying B never creates a problem for A, never creates a problem.
Okay. They basically say like some of you were asking, who the
heck cares that B walks through A? Okay. Let everybody go their
own way, ignore B, B and A are completely irrelevant to one
another. All right. Moving on. נתנו עירוב במקום אחד. Nasnu eruv bimkom
echad. Now we deal with what happens when you try to make
a unified עירוב. eruv. Now even if normally you say sometimes B
doesn't create a problem for A or A for example never creates
a problem for B because A always has A doesn't travel through
B but it does create a problem when they all became one
big group. Now that we're all together it's one bad apple spoils
the bunch so when you were separate we could have ignored you
if the problem was in A. Okay but now we're all one
big group one guy's in A is a problem it creates a
problem for everyone.
So let's take a look. נתנו עירוב במקום אחד ושכח אחד בין
מן הפנימית. Nasnu eruv bimkom echad veshachach echad bein min hapnimis. So
the גמרא Gemara limits this הלכה. halacha. מאי מקום אחד? Mai mokom
echad? What does it mean in one place? אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav חיצונה. chizona.
It means not just they're one group not that one group is
always a problem. One group is only going to always be a
problem if the עירוב eruv is in A. ומאי קרו ליה מקום
אחד? Umai karu lei mokom echad? Why do they call that one
place? One place seems to me to mean no matter where they
put the עירוב. eruv. It means מקום המיוחד לשתיהן. mokom hamiyuchad lishteihen.
It means the courtyard that they both share because effectively they both
wind up using A right? So they put the עירוב eruv in
A. Now why does it matter? So here is a very simple
point. We've made one big עירוב eruv so now if anybody sits
out they're going to create a problem for all of us. We're
one big unit and now one of the members isn't there. But
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say is if the עירוב
eruv is actually situated in a house in B then can A
carry if one guy forgot? If one guy in A forgot okay
is there any way A could carry? No even if the עירוב
eruv was just A a member of A forgot so A is
not going to be able to carry regardless. Since A is not
going to be able to carry regardless B is entitled to say
who needs you? We're going to just lock you out of our
courtyard conceptually. We have the עירוב eruv with us okay and therefore
everybody amongst us made the עירוב eruv we don't forget you you're
no longer part of our group. Now that they're allowed to say
because the עירוב eruv is with them. If the עירוב eruv had
been out here if they closed the door they don't have the
עירוב eruv anymore right? And if one of them had forgotten the
עירוב eruv then it doesn't help closing the door they've got a
problem. But if the problem is in the other courtyard right and
they're the ones with the עירוב eruv then then A is A
can't carry anyway they're not losing anything from this so we're just
going to cut you off. Okay a little amputation okay yes right
the limb has died anyway so we're going to amputate the limb
and save the rest.
Yes and they can conceptually enclose or do they actually have to
have?
No they don't have to actually close the door just conceptual.
I know that the פתח pesach and
the סגירה sgira actually do something.
Yeah but not here. Okay so let's take a look. תניא נמי
הכי Tanya nami hachi we taught similarly. נתנו עירוב בחיצונה Nasnu eruv
bachizona
if the עירוב eruv was put in A then ושכח אחד בין
מן החיצונה בין מן הפנימית veshachach echad bein min hachizona bein min
hapnimis
then whoever forgot A or B ולא עירב velo eirev שתיהן אסורות
sheteihan asuros they're both a problem. Because if an A guy because
if an A guy forgot and you wanted to cut it off
and protect B okay but B doesn't have the עירוב. eruv. If
a B guy forgot then of course you've got a problem because
if a B guy forgot right what about if that happened? If
if a B guy forgot and the עירוב eruv was in A
why doesn't A just cut off B? Why doesn't A salvage themselves?
So in theory they could except we've got a problem. Since B
is אסור asur they create a problem for A. Got it? Right?
So if so A cannot cut off B A is always influenced
by B because of this idea that B travels through. But B
is in a position to cut off A. So נתנו עירוב בפנימית
Nasnu eruv bapnimis if the עירוב eruv was in B ושכח אחד
מן הפנימית ולא עירב veshachach echad min hapnimis velo eirev if a
guy in B forgot שתיהן אסורות sheteihan asuros they're both forbidden.
What are you going to do? Right? Because you can't it doesn't
help cutting off A the problem is in B. מן החיצונה ולא
עירב Min hachizona velo eirev however if the guy in A forgot
שתיהן אסורות דברי רבי עקיבא sheteihan asuros divrei Rabbi Akiva Rabbi Akiva
says it still not going to help you right because Rabbi Akiva
says what are you going to do you want to cut you
want to cut off A? But Rabbi well actually it's not clear
why Rabbi Akiva will say it won't help. We'll get back to
that. But here Rabbi Akiva says it won't help. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim
omrim and the חכמים Chachamim. say בזו פנימית מותרת וחיצונה אסורה bezu
pnimis muteres vechizona asura in this one the the inner one is
okay. Okay so this is what we're saying if
the
עירוב eruv is in is in B and the guy who forgot
is in A so in this type of a case B is
okay they can just ignore A and they can be fine yes?
Now the question is why does Rabbi Akiva say it's a problem?
When Rabbi Akiva said that Rabbi Akiva was the one that was
more finding problems. But which one courtyard did Rabbi Akiva say was
always problematic? B? B created the problem. A was always B created
problems on A because they went through A. So Rabbi Akiva should
be prepared to agree
to
the חכמים. chachamim So why can't רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva agree, cut
off A and salvage B, right? So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says about this.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר ליה רבה בר חנה לאביי: Amar lei Rabba bar Chana le-Abaye:
מאי שנא לרבנן דאמרי פנימית מותרת? Mai shena le-rabbanan de-amri pnimis muteres?
Why did the rabbis say that B is okay because you can
sort of cut off A? משום דאחדה דשא ומשתמשא, Bishum de-achada dasha
u-mishtamsha, they could slam their door and use their courtyard, meaning conceptually,
not literally,
they can just cut off A. Okay, they have the עירוב, eiruv,
so, you know, set A adrift. So רבי עקיבא נמי תיחד דשא
ותישתמש. Rabbi Akiva nami teiched dasha ve-tishameish. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
should have agreed. This isn't based on רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva other
position. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said B influences A, but he didn't
say A influenced B, so just just cut off A. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so he said to him: עירוב מרגילה. Eiruv margila. He
says no, this is a different position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
It's not based on the earlier position, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says you can't cut them off. Once you made an עירוב eiruv
amongst A and B together, that defines us all as being together,
and we are considered in your courtyard the same way you're considered
in our courtyard. So you can't cut us off anymore. The עירוב
eiruv is מרגילת, margilas, makes us accustomed, you know, present in your
courtyard. So conceptually you see the idea that רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
it's not the same position, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is always
saying, you know, I see virtual presence of other people. I'm more
inclined to see the presence of other people that aren't physically here.
So normally A doesn't influence B, but once you made an עירוב,
eiruv, now A and B are always together and you can no
longer, you know, amputate A and cut A off. That's what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. So the גמרא Gemara
says: ורבנן נמי עירוב מרגילה. Ve-rabbanan nami eiruv margila. So that's an
issue the חכמים chachamim, should have to contend with. The עירוב eiruv
makes them one unit. The עירוב eiruv combined them. So now the
rabbis would say, דאמרה, de-amra, because B could say to A: לתיקוני
שיתפתיך ולא לעוותי. Le-tikuni shitafteich ve-lo le-avasi.
I have made you my partner so that it should be, you
know, to help me, not to make a problem for me. So
basically they could say: I no longer am interested in the עירוב.
eiruv. The עירוב eiruv was when we were all benefiting from it.
Right now you're not benefiting, you're losing and I'm losing. So we
might as well just, you know, break up the partnership. At least
I won't lose that way. Okay? So in principle you're right, B
and A became one, but at this situation B is able to
set A adrift, say we don't want it anymore. So the גמרא
Gemara says: so okay, that's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva should be open
to that argument. רבי עקיבא נמי תימא לתיקוני שיתפתיך ולא לעוותי? Rabbi
Akiva nami teima le-tikuni shitafteich ve-lo le-avasi? How would you pronounce that?
לתיקוני ולא לעוותי, Le-tikuni ve-lo le-avuti, I guess לעוותי. le-avuti. Okay, anyway,
so according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva also, why can't B sort
of say we're no longer interested in this partnership? Okay,
דאמרה ליה, de-amra lei, because here's why, because
דאמרה ליה מבטלינן לך רשותי. de-amra lei mevatlinan lach reshusi.
Because A will say to B: we have to waive our rights,
meaning basically, you can't cut us off B guys, we became one.
If you want us to step out to make it easier for
you, we would have to be מבטל mevatel our rights to you.
Now that they became one, it's one big A B חצר. chatzer.
Okay? If you want us to get out of your חצר, chatzer,
you can't do it unilaterally. We would have to first do a
ביטול bitul and essentially remove ourselves conceptually to give you back your
חצר. chatzer. So yes, I get that
now nobody can carry, and you'd like to be able to at
least carry, but you can't do it unilaterally. We were partners, we
have to at least do the act of stepping back and stepping...
Okay, so רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva saying you do ביטול.
bitul. If you do ביטול, bitul, it's fine, but until you do
ביטול, bitul, you're still partners right now. B cannot unilaterally set A
adrift, even though A isn't carrying regardless.
Can they agree on this before שבת, Shabbat, like say every שבת,
Shabbat, you know,
B is automatically מבטל mevatel or presumably...
Anyway, okay.
רבנן, Rabbanan, and the rabbis say back: אין, in, אין ביטול רשות
מחצר לחצר. ein bitul reshush me-chatzer le-chatzer. Excuse me, they say no,
remember we had this before? You can't do ביטול bitul from one
חצר chatzer to another. So in an ideal world it'll be, you
know, מענטשליך menschlich (I'm being a little facetious), but anyway it would
be מענטשליך menschlich to say that you're not going to unilaterally cut
A adrift. A would have to, you know, remove their rights from
B and they would have to agree to sort of withdraw. But
they say ביטול bitul doesn't work from A to B. So we
can't ask for it. So since we can't ask for it anyway,
it would be meaningless. So now we can just say B can
cut A adrift unilaterally. Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara now
got down to the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the
חכמים, Chachamim that conceptually what we're trying to do is cut A
adrift, maybe we can't do that because... as they have been made
into one unit because of the עירוב, eruv, and the חכמים Chachamim
and Rabbi Akiva says therefore A has to do an act of
withdrawing, and the חכמים Chachamim say that act would be meaningless, so
therefore B can just unilaterally cut them adrift. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. לימא שמואל ורבי יוחנן בפלוגתא דרבנן ורבי
עקיבא קמיפלגי. Leima Shmuel v'Rabbi Yochanan b'plugta d'Rabbanan v'Rabbi Akiva kamifligi.
The debate of Shmuel and Rabbi Yochanan, which is this debate of
can you do ביטול bittul from one חצר chatzer to another, that
seems to now be the way we're framing the debate of Rabbi
Akiva and the רבנן, Rabbanan, because we're now saying their ultimate debate
boils down to can you do ביטול bittul from A to B.
Where were we? דשמואל אמר כרבנן. D'Shmuel amar k'Rabbanan.
Shmuel who says you can't do ביטול מחצר לחצר bittul mechatzer l'chatzer,
is like the Rabbis. They say it's meaningless for A to do
ביטול bittul to B, so it's not needed because it's meaningless. ורבי
יוחנן דאמר כרבי עקיבא. V'Rabbi Yochanan d'amar k'Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Yochanan says
you can do ביטול מחצר לחצר, bittul mechatzer l'chatzer, and that's like
Rabbi Akiva who would say until A has done ביטול, bittul they're
still all in it together. So אמר לך שמואל, amar lach Shmuel,
so no, the גמרא Gemara is going to say it's not necessarily
connected. Shmuel could say to you, אנא דאמרי אפילו רבי עקיבא, ana
d'amri afilu Rabbi Akiva, I, who normally say you can't do ביטול
מחצר לחצר, bittul mechatzer l'chatzer. I could say here like Rabbi Akiva
that in this case you can. Why? עד כאן לא קאמר רבי
עקיבא הכא, ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Akiva hacha, here Rabbi Akiva
says you have to do ביטול bittul, A to B, אלא בשתי
חצרות זו לפנים מזו, ela bishtei chatzerot zu lifnim mizu, because they're
much more inherently one unit. They're back to back and B is
always present in A. So here where they really are, you know,
falling on top of one another, it's not so much two חצרות.
chatzerot. And therefore I will allow ביטול, bittul you know, that's why
Rabbi Akiva says you can do ביטול מחצר לחצר. bittul mechatzer l'chatzer
דאסרן אהדדי, d'asran ahadadei,
and B creates problems for A. So when they create problems, they're
much more one חצר. chatzer. And if you remember that was part
of Shmuel's idea, that when you can do ביטול מחצר לחצר bittul
mechatzer l'chatzer. if they are influencing one another. So here they're influencing
one another, yes, therefore Rabbi Akiva would say A is able to
do ביטול bittul, and therefore required to do ביטול. bittul אבל התם,
aval hatam, what we were talking about like a week ago, מי
קאסרן אהדדי, mi kaasran ahadadei, the courtyards weren't influencing one another and
when they weren't influencing one another, you cannot do ביטול bittul. from
one to the other. So Shmuel says generally I can say you
can't do ביטול, bittul here you should be allowed to because they're
much more one courtyard. ורבי יוחנן, V'Rabbi Yochanan, and Rabbi Yochanan who
says
normally you can do ביטול bittul, one to the other, אמר, amar,
אנא דאמרי אפילו רבנן, ana d'amri afilu Rabbanan, I could say even
like the Rabbis. The Rabbis who say that you don't have to
do ביטול. bittul Why don't you have to do ביטול bittul. if
normally you're able to do ביטול bittul from one courtyard to the
other? We should demand it here. עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן הכא
אלא דאמר ליה אדמבטלת לי קאסרת עלי. ad kan lo ka'amrei Rabbanan
hacha ela d'amar leh ad mivatlet li kaasrat alai.
Until now we're saying why did the Rabbis say that A does
not have to withdraw from B? Because they're not able to. You
can't do ביטול bittul from one courtyard to the other. But now
what Rabbi Yochanan is saying is, no, you know what, in theory
A could do ביטול bittul to B, but there's no need because
B basically says to A, look, before you get around to doing
ביטול, bittul you're already creating a headache for me. Meaning, you know,
you here because of your participation in this עירוב, eruv, you've created
a problem A. So
therefore אדמבטלת
לי, ad mivatlet li, before you get around to doing ביטול, bittul,
קאסרת עלי, kaasrat alai, you've already made things forbidden to me. So
who needs your ביטול? bittul, Meaning I'm going to set you adrift.
Meaning it's basically the simple point that I'm entitled to cut you
off. Okay, אבל התם מי קאסרן אהדדי, aval hatam mi kaasran ahadadei,
but there, you know, there's none of that idea. Meaning the basic
point being that the רבנן Rabbanan could hold normally you have the
option of doing ביטול bittul? if it helps you. But here the
fact that in theory A could do ביטול bittul because, so when
you have remember courtyards that forgot and you want to do ביטול
bittul to enable you to carry in a courtyard, there you could
say fine you could do ביטול מחצר לחצר. bitul mechatzar lechatzar But
here what he's saying is we're not going to demand that A
do ביטול. bittul A is creating problems for B, B doesn't need
A, B's entitled to cut off the relationship and set A adrift
unilaterally even without ביטול, bittul. even if in theory ביטול bittul, might
be possible, it's not needed. Okay, so that's the upshot of this
debate is
you have I mean you have one unit, they become one unit.
How much when it's injuring one party, and I do want to
emphasize it that it is unilateral but A isn't being hurt in
the process, right? A forgot, so A isn't going to be able
to carry regardless. So now the new partnership is hurting them. B
has the עירוב, eruv, can B unilaterally cut off A is the
debate. And the חכמים Chachamim say yes, and Rabbi Akiva says no,
and the גמרא Gemara says it's not the exact same position of
Rabbi Akiva, but again Rabbi Akiva says once you're a unit then
you know it's harder to get rid of the other presence. And
Rabbi Akiva says A would have to actively withdraw from the partnership,
they would have to do ביטול bittul and he holds it's allowed.
And the חכמים chachamim, say A does not have to and B
can cut them out. Either because doing a withdrawal would be meaningless,
אין מבטלין מחצר לחצר, ein mivatlin mechatzer l'chatzer, or because even if
it wouldn't be meaningless it's not necessary, we don't have to you
know we can cut them off unilaterally, they're just hurting us and
they're not helping
us. That's a good point. You know, if he was actually מבטל
mevatel his own רשות, reshus, then you know it's actually a funny
point because when רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says that if they want
to cut off A, A has to do ביטול, bittul why would
A do ביטול bitul, to B? Why wouldn't just the one guy
who forgot do ביטול bitul to the rest of the people in
A and make everybody happy? Or do, I guess that's also a
ביטול bitul מחצר לחצר mechatzer l'chatzer because he's also, oh that's what
the גמרא Gemara discussed before. He's directly being מבטל mevatel to A
but it also influences B, but same point. If רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva says you can do מחצר לחצר, mechatzar lechatzar, just have the
guy in A do ביטול. bitul.
It's a good point.
But if he's been מבטל mevatel to everybody else in
A then there's no מחצר לחצר mechatzar lechatzar anymore because
he now has an עירוב. eruv.
Right, right, it's a good point. Unless the point is that the
other people of A are doing the ביטול. bitul. They're the ones
that still,
that they're, yeah. That's a good question. That's a good question. It's,
you know, it's more of a hypothetical that A has to do
ביטול bitul because if A is actually doing ביטול, bitul, right, then
they can solve the problem in a much easier way. So that's
a very good point actually. Let me just see whatever if רש״י
Rashi addresses this, one minute.
Yeah, no, רש״י Rashi doesn't address that, so that's a very good
point. You're right. I mean if they really wanted to solve it,
that one guy would do ביטול. bitul. So maybe we're just talking
about in theory they should be required or maybe we're talking about
the other people in A are doing ביטול bitul to B. But
in theory you're right, you know, if the one guy who forgot
did ביטול, bitul, everybody should be happy. Okay, so let's now see
as the last part of the משנה. mishnah. אם היו שני יחידים,
im hayu shenei yechidim,
if A and B there's only one person in each courtyard then
שלום על ישראל. shalom al yisrael. They don't need an עירוב. eruv.
A is good, B is good. Does B influence A? According to
the חכמים, chachamim, no. So everybody is happy. אמר רב יוסף, amar
Rav Yosef, תני רבי, tani Rebbi, היו גמל אסורין. hayu gimel asurin.
If there were three people in the two courtyards, two in one
and one in the other, then it would be a problem.
So now, why would it be a problem? Because there are two
scenarios.
This is very easy.
Right? What are the two scenarios of three people in two courtyards?
Okay, there is, right, one
and
one and one and two. Okay.
So they could have oh three and three or three and
zero, but that's a bit ridiculous, very cute.
Okay, anyway, so anyway right as he has it here. Okay. So
anyway, in this case, according to the חכמים, chachamim it should be
fine. Meaning A can't carry in their own courtyard if there's no
עירוב, eruv, right? But B can carry and, you know, and that
should be fine, right? In this type of a case, okay, B
can't carry and because B can't carry, A can't
carry, right? A still has an opening to the רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, right? So because B can't carry in this case, A can't
carry, right? Because according to חכמים chachamim, it's אוסרת. oseret. So this
one they're both אסור. assur.
Okay, what should the הלכה halacha be here in this one?
A is אסור assur and B should be מותר. mutar. It's one
guy and A doesn't influence him. Okay, but he says that according
to רבי, Rebbi, whenever there are three it's always אסור. assur. So
why is this אסור? assur? And the answer is that this is
going to be אסור assur because it's going to be confused with
this one. This one B really should be מותר, mutar, but we're
going to say אסור assur because you'll confuse it with the other.
Didn't say that in the other case we had before? Forget about
three.
Yeah, I know. Okay, anyway, let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
is going to reject it anyway, or sort of reject it. Anyway,
אמר ליה רב ביבי. amar lei Rav Bibi. Okay, so אמר רב
יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, תני רבי, tani Rebbi, היו גמל אסורין, hayu
gimel asurin, and whenever there are three it's a problem. אמר ליה
רב ביבי, amar lei Rav Bibi, so רב ביבי Rav Bibi said
to the students or the rabbis, לא תציתו ליה, lo tetzitu lei,
don't listen to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Remember again, this has come
up a lot in עירובין, Eruvin, that רב יוסף Rav Yosef first
of all says a lot of things and he often gets them
wrong and he forgets what he said. So that's like you know
the prevalent in different מסכתות masechtos in different topics of certain rabbinic
figures you know is very interesting that there are different you know
concentrations. Anyway, don't listen to רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. אנא אמריתא ניהליה,
ana amrisani alei,
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said this in the name of רבי Rebbi
but he forgot. I was the one who told it to him,
not רבי. Rebbi. ומשמיה דרב אדא בר אבא אמריתא ניהליה, umeshmei deRav
Adda bar Abba amrisani alei, and I told it to him in
the name of רב אדא בר אבא. Rav Adda bar Abba. הוא,
hu, and here's the explanation, דנקרא בהן רבים בחיצונה. denikra bahen rabbim
bachitzona.
Since there's a רבים, rabbim, right, in the outer one, so there's
an idea that this here's a case that there's a רבים, rabbim,
it's not just a יחיד. yachid. So you'll confuse this case of
a רבים rabbim where B should be מותר mutar with this case
of a רבים rabbim where everybody is אסור. assur. So because there's
a presence of a רבים, rabbim, it's not pure יחידית, yechidit, it's
not one and one, the difference between these two cases is easily
mixed up and therefore it's a problem. So he got it, meaning
the הלכה halacha is right, but it was in the name of
a different person and I said the reason was because of the
רבים. rabbim. I got confused. He told me רבים. rabbim. He says
this is אסור assur because of רבים. rabbim. And I remembered that
he said it's אסור assur because of רבי. Rebbi.
So I said it in the name of רבי, Rebbi, but what
he said to me was it's a problem because of רבים. rabbim.
So it's quite fascinating, right? You see that mix-up of similar like
things that sound the same. Okay, so that's the position of רב
יוסף Rav Yosef in the name of either רבים rabbim or רבי.
Rebbi. ושמואל אמר, u-Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says לעולם מותרת עד שיהיו
שנים בפנימית ואחד בחיצונה. le'olam mutteres ad she-yehiyu shenayim bi-pnimis v'echad be-chitzonah.
We're not making this לא פלוג. lo plug. Okay, this case here
where one is in B is totally fine. B is totally fine.
אמר רב אלעזר. amar Rav Elazar. So רב אלעזר Rav Elazar said,
ונכרי הרי הוא כרבים. v'nochri harei hu ke-rabbim. Let's say even according
to שמואל, Shmuel, let's say this one guy here was a נכרי.
nochri. Okay, so what's—excuse me, wait, that wouldn't make a difference because
no, no, no, because then B—it's irrelevant for B and two is
anyway אסור. assur. Wait, let me remember which case is this.
One
minute.
דאמר נכרי בפנימית ושני ישראלים בחיצונה אוסרת דריסת רגלו עליהן עד שישכיר.
de-amar nochri bi-pnimis u-shenei Yisraelim be-chitzonah oseres drisas raglo aleihen ad she-yaskir.
וליבא דשמואל, v'aliba de-Shmuel, right? Oh, it is this one, but the
question is... Oh, I guess the point just is that even if
they make—right—even in this way, until now we've been talking about they
haven't made an עירוב. eiruv. That's really the point. Okay, but in
this case even if they basically go ahead and make an עירוב,
eiruv, the נכרי nochri is going to be a problem. It'll be
like רבים rabbim and according to the חכמים, once there's a רבים
rabbim in B, B is an issue. Fine. That's the only point.
So now A has made an עירוב eiruv and if there's a
one person here it's not a problem. If there's multiple people here,
it's אוסרת במקומה, oseres bi-mekomah, it's אוסר שלא במקומה oser shelo bi-mekomah
unless you're שוכר—unless socher you're שוכר, socher, right. But he says even
the individual נכרי nochri is a problem until you're שוכר. socher. Let's
take a look. אמר רב אלעזר ונכרי הרי הוא כרבים. amar Rav
Elazar v'nochri harei hu ke-rabbim.
If there's an individual נכרי, nochri, it's like many people are in
B and it creates a problem even if there's an עירוב eiruv
in A. Now, מאי שנא ישראל דלא אסר? mai shena Yisrael de-lo
assar? Now, one minute, why is it different? If the guy would
be a Jew in B, he wouldn't make it אסור. assur. דמאן
דידע ידע. de-man de-yada yada. Because
if people—if you know there's a single Jew in B, so meaning
if this guy is a Jew, right? We said it's okay, right?
And A made an עירוב, eiruv, A can carry as well. Now,
why won't somebody say 'Oh, how is A carrying, you know, there
are many people living in B, they create a problem? It's because
they know the הלכה, halacha, it's אוסרת במקומה, oseres bi-mekomah, you know,
it's אוסר—it's oser אוסר oser or whatever.' So A, maybe they know
it's only one Jew and then שלום על ישראל. shalom al Yisrael.
Okay, then they won't be bothered by the fact that A is
carrying.
ומן דידע ידע, u-man de-yada yada, דלא ידע de-lo yada and if
you don't realize that B is only one person, סבר אגורי אגיר,
savar agori agir, I'm sorry, סבר, savar, I'm sorry, עירובי עריב. eiruvi
ayriv. If you see them carrying in A and you think there
are many people in B, you'll assume A and B made one
big עירוב. eiruv. Okay, so there's no problem allowing, going back to
the case of the משנה, mishna, one Jew and making an עירוב.
eiruv. Either they'll know it's one Jew and therefore they'll know it's
okay, or they'll think you all made one big עירוב. eiruv. נכרי.
nochri. So the גמרא Gemara says, so okay, if it's a non-Jew
as well. נכרי נמי אמרינן. nochri nami amrinan. דידע ידע. de-yada yada.
If you know there's only one guy, you know there's only one
guy and that's why B can carry.
ודלא ידע, u-de-lo yada, and if you're not aware that it's only
one guy and you think maybe there are many non-Jews there or
something, סבר אגורי אגיר. savar agori agir. You'll assume, okay, but you
did שכירות sechirus from the non-Jew, you rented it from the non-Jew.
So why is any of this a problem? So the גמרא Gemara
says, no. סתם נכרי אי איכא דאוגיר מיפרסמי. stam nochri ei ika
de-ogir mifarsmei. In a normal case by a non-Jew, if he actually
agreed to rent, מיפרסמי mifarsmei he would talk about it or there
would be, you know, there'd be a report about it. So basically
it means you're not renting from this guy because people know—no, no,
no, if they had rented from the non-Jew, we would have heard
about it. So they know there's no rental, they know there's a
non-Jew living here, okay. So they think why are you carrying in
A? What about the fact that there are people living in B?
And we know you didn't do a rental. And they might not
realize either that it's only one guy and because it's one guy
it's not a problem, or they might not realize that the הלכה
halacha is that with... So they know there's no rental. They know
there's a non-Jew living here, okay? So they think, why are you
carrying in A? What about the fact that there are people living
in B, and we know you didn't do a rental? And they
might not realize either that it's only one guy, and because it's
only one guy, it's not a problem, or they might not realize
that the הלכה halacha is that with one guy it's okay. So
therefore, that will be a problem. They won't realize the situation and
they'll think that even if there are multiple people in B, that
you can go ahead and carry in A. Okay, so that's why
we will not allow that one case. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, let's do one more case. י' בתים
זו זו לפנים מזו. Yud Batim Zo Zo Lifnim MiZo. Okay, so
this is similar to the case we ended with yesterday.
You have ten houses, all
attached townhouses, okay? One behind the other.
זו לפנים מזו. Zo Lifnim MiZo. פנימי נותן את עירובו ודיו. Pnimi
Noten Es Eruvo BeDayo. The inner one gives his עירוב eruv and
that is enough. So what you basically have is the inner one,
I'm sorry, the inner one. So basically what you have is you've
got, now we get away from the whole A and B for
a
minute, you've got one courtyard and this house opens in and then
you've got this row
of
townhouses. But only the outer townhouse opens up into the yard. All
of these other people
don't have any direct access into the yard. So you only need
one עירוב, eruv, okay? Actually, no, פנימי נותן ודיו. Pnimi Noten BeDayo.
We're going to see that in a minute. Actually, the inner one
gives and that's good for everybody. So why is that? You only
need one, but we're going to see why we articulated as פנימי.
pnimi. Let's take a look.
Okay, so it says like this: פנימי נותן את עירובו ודיו. Pnimi
Noten Es Eruvo BeDayo. רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו חיצון, Rabbi Yochanan Amar
Afilu Chitzon, even the outer one can give the עירוב. eruv. They're
all one and even the outer one. So now we're going to
see what's at stake. חיצון בית שער הוא. Chitzon Beis Sha'ar Hu.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, the outer one isn't in
this case conceptually a house, it's really like an ante-chamber, right? A
בית שער beis sha'ar was sort of like the little guardhouse they
had by a gate. So what the גמרא Gemara says here is,
conceptually, this is the real house and all of these are, all
you guys are living in a big gatehouse in front of my
house. So I'm the one, since I'm the one that goes through
all of you, I'm the guy in the back and considered to
be the real tenant of this and you're all just living in
a gatehouse. Okay, and therefore I get it.
So the other opinion, who was the other opinion who said the
חיצון? chitzon? רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said one of the outer guys can give. So
the גמרא Gemara says, how can an outer guy give? He's in
a gatehouse. So the גמרא Gemara says,
חיצון של פנימי. chitzon shel pnimi. No, what we don't mean is
we don't mean any of the outer ones, we mean the penultimate
one. So he's also considered an inhabitant and not in a gatehouse.
במאי קמיפלגי? Bmai Kamifligi? What's the debate? מר סבר בית שער דיחיד
שמי בית שער, Mar Savar Beis Sha'ar DeYachid Shmai Beis Sha'ar, that
you can even have a gatehouse for a single
house, ומר סבר לא שמי בית שער, veMar Savar lo shmai beis
sha'ar, you can't have a gatehouse for a single house.
So everybody agrees
this guy back here is the real house and everybody goes through.
Everybody agrees that all these guys, since they have people trampling through
them, are effectively considered בית שער beis sha'ar gatehouse. The question is
how about the penultimate guy, this guy? Is he a בית שער
beis sha'ar for one guy? Is there a concept of a gatehouse
for a single house? So maybe there isn't. So if there's no
concept of a gatehouse for a single house, then these two are
the real houses and those are the gatehouses. If there is a
concept, then all of
these,
anyway, so this is effectively the idea. It's just worth noting that
without the idea of בית שער, beis sha'ar, what we're really saying
is, and this way it is connected to yesterday, is all these
attached houses are all considered one unit. Only one of them opens
up. They only have to contribute one עירוב eruv because only one
of them opens up into the חצר. chatzer. So which one conceptually
of this unit is the real בעל הבית baal bayis of the
house? You could have said anybody, right? But here we're conceptualizing it
as the guy in the back because he travels through all the
rest and in that way it's similar to the discussion of B
and A. If you're going through, what are the implications? So the
guys in the back are the real owners, everybody else is effectively
in the gatehouse. More of that tomorrow.
Alright.